Okay, well. When we were talking about the different cases about whether
one witness says בפני נכתב bifnei nechtav or one says בפני נחתם
bifnei nechtam or two and one and whatever that whole מחלוקת machloket
between רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, and
we mentioned that they were two possible
ways of
looking at whether two witnesses that come from מדינת הים, medinat hayam,
do they have to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם bifnei nechtav uvifnei
nechtam or not? Right? So version one has it that they don't
have to, and version two had it that they did, and we
weren't really sure as to which
way we go at the end. We're continuing this and we're picking
up with רבה בר בר חנה חלש Rabba bar bar Chana chalash
about six lines from the bottom of the עמוד ב amud bet
of the prior דף. daf. So רבה בר בר חנה חלש, Rabba
bar bar Chana chalash, so he was sick, ולגבי רבי יהודה ורבה
לשיילוביה. uligabei Rabbi Yehuda v'Rabba l'shailuvei. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
רבה Rabba came to visit him, a ביקור חולים bikur cholim visit.
So בעו מיניה שנים שהביאו גט ממדינת הים צריכים שיאמרו בפני נכתב
ובפני נחתם או אין צריכים. Ba'u minei shnayim sheheviu get m'medinat hayam
tzrichim sheyomru bifnei nechtav uvifnei nechtam o ein tzrichim. So do they
have to say it or not?
So אמר להן אין צריכים. Amar lahen ein tzrichim. And he gives
a pretty good logical proof for that. ואלו יאמרו בפנינו גירשה מי
לא מהימני? v'ilu yomru bifneinu gorshah mi lo meheimni? So if they
just forget about the whole thing about בפני נכתב בפני נחתם, bifnei
nechtav bifnei nechtam, they're just there and they're basically like עדי מסירה,
edei mesirah, right? עדי מסירה edei mesirah would work. So if they
were witnesses to the actual divorce, they would have been believed. So
certainly if they didn't say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, bifnei nechtav uvifnei
nechtam, they would not be a problem. So עד הכי אתא ההוא
חברא. Ad hachi ata hahu chavara. Then this is like, alright, now
that was basically the ruling. The story continues and the end of
the story has nothing to do with the beginning part of it.
But nevertheless, it does make for an
interesting incident. So it says עד הכי אתא ההוא חברא. ad hachi
ata hahu chavara. Now sometimes you have the חברים chaverim which were
the learned people
who are like people who
are חברים, chaverim, like we even have that in Yekkish circles, people
call a חבר chaver so-and-so. But over here in this case, it
is not the learned people, rather it's these Persian ruffians basically. So
רש"י Rashi says פרסאי. Parsai. שקלו לשרגא מקמייהו. Shaklu l'sharga mikamaihu.
So they took the candle from in front of them. And as
רש"י Rashi explains, it happened to have been like one of their
holidays and the only people allowed to have light were in the
temples.
So that
was a big no-no because I guess this was happening either at
night or this was a conversation
that was happening in the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. It wasn't so
well lit anyway, so they took the candle from away from them
and they couldn't see anything anymore. So אמר, amar, so then he
said, רחמנא, Rachmana, you know, Merciful One,
או בטולך או בטולא דבר עשיו. o betulach o betula d'bar Eisav.
So either here he's translating בטולך betulach is in Your shade or
in the shade of the son of Esau. In other words, either
protect us, Hashem, or you know, we don't want to have to
deal with these
פרסאי, Parsai, these Persians. You
know, הלואי halevai we would have been in the גלות galut of
בני עשיו, b'nei Eisav, the Romans.
So ארומאי מעלו מפרסאי? Aroma'ei ma'alu miParsai? The Romans were better than
the פרסאי? Parsai? In other words,
so I guess this is
old. The פרסאי, Parsai, this is going back quite a while, right?
So are the... because Romans lasted for quite a while.
So the Romans, you know, were better?
והתניא רבי חייא מאי
דכתיב
אלקים הבין דרכה והוא ידע
את מקומה? v'hanya Rabbi Chiyya mai d'chtiv Elokim hevin darkah v'hu yada
et mkomah? So God knew its ways and knew its place. יודע
הקדוש ברוך הוא בישראל שאין יכולין לקבל גזירות הרומיים עמד והגלה אותם
לבבל. Yodeia HaKadosh Baruch Hu b'Yisrael she'ein yecholin lekabel gzeirot haRomiyim amad
v'higlah otam l'Bavel. So God knew that they
couldn't live under the Romans, so therefore He exiled them to בבל,
Bavel, which means it's better to be in בבל Bavel than be
under the Romans. And you're a second ago saying הלואי halevai we're
under the Romans. לא קשיא הא מקמי דאתו חברי
לבבל הא בתר דאתו חברי לבבל. Lo kashya ha mikamei d'atu chaverei
l'Bavel ha batar d'atu chaverei l'Bavel. So it depends, you know, before
these... so apparently like, you know, there were those who were the
original Persians and now there were, later on, these חברים chaverim came,
whatever you want to call them.
So once the חברים chaverim came, you know, then the whole thing
went to pot. There goes the neighborhood. But until then it wasn't
so bad. So yeah, so the Romans are better than these חברים,
chaverim, but the Persians were better than the Romans.
So that's how it goes. Anyway, that really had nothing to do
with that point. Now we're going to get back to it. אמר
רבי אמי אמר רבי יוחנן לא שנו אלא שגט יוצא מתחת ידי
עדי כתיבה. Amar Rabbi Ami amar Rabbi Yochanan lo shanu ela sheget
yotzei mitachat yedei edei chtivah. So this was the case of אחד
אומר בפני נכתב ושנים אומרים בפנינו נחתם, echad omer bifnei nechtav ushnayim
omrim bifneinu nechtam, right? Which is towards the end of the משנה
Mishnah that we had over here. One says... בפני נכתב bifanai nechtav
and two said בפנינו נחתם bifanenu nechtam we said that that was
כשר. kasher. Right then and we were dealing with yesterday whether
who was like the main שליח shliach for it? Right was it
you know we have יוצא מתחת ידי כולם yotzei mitachat yedei kulam
were they all roped into this or just some of them roped
into it i don't know if you remember we that was one
of the questions we had yesterday that you know oh it's כשר
kasher oh but wait but everyone might agree that if you know
if they're all involved that it would be the case would be
different or everyone might say that
whatever those were all the permutations that we dealt with
yesterday we're gonna revisit this slightly. So the case that we just
mentioned that one said בפני נכתב bifanai nechtav and two said בפנינו
נחתם bifanenu nechtam was כשר kasher and that was something that everyone
agreed to. He qualifies this by saying לא שנו אלא שהגט יוצא
מתחת יד עד כתיבה. lo shanu ela sheget yotze mitachat yad ed
ktiva. Right the one guy right the one guy said it's נכתב.
nechtav. So he's the main guy.
Any other two are just sort of like you know there just
incidentally then that would be okay and i don't 100% get this
he's like דנעשו כשניים על זה וכשניים על זה. d'naasu k'shnayim al
zeh v'shnayim al zeh. So it's like two and two. So since
he's the שליח shliach and he's able to say בפני נכתב bifanai
nechtav so he's sort of like you know upgraded his set he's
as good as two and then these are obviously two so this
so it's like two and two so then so then you're fine.
אבל מתחת יד עדי חתימה פסול. aval mitachat yad edei chatima pasul.
So
but if it's only these two guys that they're the main guy
then this guy is coming along they just have the only have
people that are saying בפני נכתב bifanai nechtav and and you know
and as we know you need to say you have to have
a combination of בפני נכתב bifanai nechtav בפני נכתב. bifanai nechtav. So
אלמא קסבר alma kasavar
anyway but the point is שניים שהביאו גט ממדינת הים צריכים שיאמרו
בפנינו נכתב ובפנינו נחתם. shnayim sheheviu get midinat hayam tzrichim sheyomru bifanenu
nechtav uvfanenu nechtam. Right. So
meaning if these are the two main guys this guy isn't upgraded
so you just have two and one right? But if this guy
the number one guy you know the first guy the guy says
בפנינו נכתב bifanenu nechtav נכתב nechtav so
so now it's two and two and between between them all you're
saying בפנינו נכתב ובפנינו נחתם bifanenu nechtav bifanenu nechtam right and you
have two meaning the two have to say it. So and you
are and you're getting it that way. So that's what he says.
So אמר ליה רב אסי אלא מעתה רישא דקתני amar leh rav
assi ela me'ata resha dekatani שניים אומרים בפנינו נכתב ואחד אומר בפני
נכתב shnayim omrim bifanenu nechtav ve'echad omer bifanai nechtav now
this case the two say בפנינו נכתב bifanenu nechtav and then one
says בפני נכתב bifanai nechtav which was a מחלוקת machloket בין תנא
קמא beine tanakamma ורבי יהודה ve'rabbi yehuda פסול pasul ורבי יהודה מכשיר.
ve'rabbi yehuda machshir.
So אפילו גט יוצא מתחת יד שניהם פסלו רבנן. afilu get yotze
mitachat yad shneihem paslu rabbanan. So even if the גט get would
be in front of these two would be from these two רבנן
rabbanan would be פסול pasul because you know because then you have
two and this guy is only one right? And and you need
שניים shnayim you know and if we're saying that שניים שהביאו shnayim
sheheviu you know you both you have to get two בפנינו נכתב
bifanenu nechtav and two בפנינו נחתם bifanenu nechtams right then you only
have two and one. So would the רבנן rabbanan even say in
that kind of a case it'd be פסול? pasul? אמר ליה אין.
amar leh in. Yeah exactly.
But וזימנין אחריתי דיתיב וקאמר v'zina achidei dyasev veka'amar דאפילו גט יוצא
מתחת יד עדי חתימה
כשר.
d'afilu get yotze mitachat yad edei
chatima kasher. But you know other times you know you were learning
this and and you said it'd be good right? Not not even
you know the רבנן rabbanan would be פסול pasul but even a
case would be good. So if you're gonna say it's good אלמא
קסבר שניים שהביאו גט ממדינת הים אין צריכים שיאמרו בפנינו נכתב ובפנינו
נחתם. alma kasavar shnayim sheheviu get midinat hayam ein tzrichim sheyomru bifanenu
nechtav uvfanenu nechtam. So you know if you've learned it that way
then they don't have to say it. And then אמר ליה רב
אסי amar leh rav assi if that's what you're gonna say that
if it's gonna be good אלא מעתה רישא דקתני ela me'ata resha
dekatani שניים אומרים בפנינו נכתב ואחד אומר בפני נכתב פסול ורבי יהודה
מכשיר. shnayim omrim bifanenu nechtav ve'echad omer bifanai nechtav pasul ve'rabbi yehuda
machshir. So
what about the case that's a מחלוקת? machloket? Right if you're gonna
say that this case
you know that this case would be good and then this case
would be a מחלוקת machloket and if you hold you don't need
to say that שניים שהביאו shnayim sheheviu if you right in other
words if you hold that you do then it's stricter if you
hold that you don't obviously it's more lenient. So in that kind
of a case that it's a
מחלוקת machloket פסול pasul ורבי יהודה מכשיר ve'rabbi yehuda machshir טעמא דלא
גט יוצא מתחת יד שניהם ta'ama de'lo get yotzei mitachat yad shneihem
but if it would היוצא מתחת ידי שניהם hayotzei mitachat yedei shneihem
then you can be more lenient because we just hold right that
if two are coming you don't have if you have two right?
Then you don't have to say בפנינו נכתב ובפנינו נחתם. bifanenu nechtav
uvfanenu nechtam. So if you don't have to say it then in
that case if it's היוצא מתחת ידי שניהם hayotzei mitachat yedei shneihem
then מכשיר רבנן machshir rabbanan then רבנן rabbanan would say it's okay.
Right if it was only if it was only יוצא מתחת יד
אחד מהם yotze mitachat yad echad meihem right then that'd be a
problem. But if היוצא מתחת ידי שניהם hayotzei mitachat yedei shnayim and
two don't who are coming you don't have to say בפנינו נכתב
ובפנינו נחתם. bifanenu nechtav uvfanenu nechtam. It's only when it's one because
you know what based on what we said before maybe it'll be
אתי לאחלופי בקיום שטר דעלמא ati le'achlufi b'kiyum shtara d'alma you'll come
to confuse it with a קיום שטר דעלמא kiyum shtara d'alma of
say one is good for that which it isn't but if two
you don't have that that worry right? So if you can be
more lenient by two then why did the רבנן rabbanan say it's
פסול? pasul? It would only be because it's you know because it's
from this guy but if it's coming from the hands of If
it's, you know, if you're really having two and two don't need
to say it, you're adopting that position, then the רבנן Rabbanan would
be מכשיר machshir it. So אמר ליה אין, amar leh in, בהא
זימנא לא אמרת הכי, b'ha zimna lo amarta hachi, but before, you
know, we just got through saying before, just the opposite, right? If
you know, like, you said just the opposite, that שנים באים ממדינת
הים, shnayim baim mimedinas hayam, צריכים שיאמרו בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, tzrichim
sheyomru b'fanai nichtav uv'fanai nechtam, that if they're, if two are coming,
they do have to say it. Now you're saying they don't have
to say it, we can be more lenient. Before you said that
they do have to say it and we have to be more
strict. So which is it? So am I going too fast or
are we all
set?
Yeah? Okay.
Basically the question is, you know, as with yesterday I'll just recapitulate.
Yesterday, you know, we were going through if two come from מדינת
הים, medinas hayam, do you have to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם,
b'fanai nichtav uv'fanai nechtam, right? So we just went through this whole,
you know, we just went through these all, this whole מחלוקת, machlokes,
and basically what we were trying to do is figure out which
view it holds, right? Was it they do have to say it
or they don't have to say it? If they do have to
say it then we're more strict and if they don't have to
say it we're more lenient. So basically, so this, you know,
this rabbi sort of had it both ways. So he wanted to
know which way are you going, right? You said one time you
said version one, one time you said version two. So which are
you holding? That's basically what we're, that's basically what we're where we're
at. So,
אמר ליה יתד היא שלא תמוט. amar leh yated hi shelo tamut.
So
no, you know, this is an unmovable like, you know, peg, meaning
like you know, you can, you can place your trust in this.
This last, this later version, you know, meaning I've basically retracted and
now I really think that they don't have to say it. So
if they don't have to say it, we'll be more lenient. So
again, so if we would be more lenient, why would the רבנן
Rabbanan say it's פסול? pasul? The answer is because that would be
a case שאין הגט יוצא מתחת ידי שניהם, she'ein haget yotzei mitachas
yedei shneihem, because it's not being brought by, you know, the two
guys are not the, are not the, you know, the main guys.
So therefore
we
are more strict, but if they were then, you know, they don't
have to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, b'fanai nichtav uv'fanai nechtam, we're
fine. All right, now we're going to move away from this topic
and we'll get to another topic, new משנה. mishna. It is a
different topic
and we'll
just erase this. We'll get into another
important מחלוקת. machlokes. So the first משנה mishna was basically the מחלוקת
machlokes of רבה Rabbah and רבא Rava as to why do you
need to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם? b'fanai nichtav uv'fanai nechtam? Was
it because of an issue of לשמה lishmah or was it because
you just, you know, are worried about
אין עדים מצויים לקיימו? ein eidim metzuyim lekaymo? Then we dealt with
these offshoots about let's say you have two in one and one
says part of it, the other says the other part of it
and all those permutations. Now we're going to deal with a
important concept of גט מוקדם. get mukdam. You know, this whole thing
isn't even working.
Let's just issue, go back to one thing. What was the final?
The final conclusion was that two people who, that if you have
שנים באים ממדינת הים, shnayim baim mimedinas hayam, right? The whole case
was from abroad because you know, or whatever those concerns were, right?
Are we also as strict or are we more lenient? So the
answer is more lenient. If two come, you don't have to say
all this בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. b'fanai nichtav uv'fanai nechtam.
They don't have to say it if two come and say, they
don't have to say anything because they're two and the conclusion was
they could have been witnesses to the divorce anyway.
Well that was what we said on the עמוד א', amud aleph,
yeah, you know, as to how much the עמוד ב' amud beis
is going on the עמוד א', amud aleph, you know, as to
why the reason is, you know, it's not, it's not certain, but
yeah, so you are more lenient, yeah.
In the end, two people come with the גט, get, they don't
have to say anything.
Right.
That's what it seems like. So,
you
know, but as to
do we say that they should say some of it or, you
know, it's a little unclear again how much the עמוד א' amud
aleph over here is going versus the last part of the עמוד
ב' amud beis when we had the very logical
view that they said, you know, they didn't say anything, right?
That would be good. In other words, remember we also had these
concepts that if they start saying something, then you're in trouble, like
you got to do everything כדת חכמים, k'das chachamim, right? Sometimes like
doing a half job can get you in trouble, right? Remember that?
Like in other words, and that was the other question I had
the other day, you know, that like if they just said בפני
נכתב, b'fanai nichtav, you know, let's say they just would have been
עדי מסירה, eidei mesira, they would have said nothing, you know, that
would have been good. But like once they start saying something, right,
you sort of trip yourself up by starting to say something and
not finishing it, right? So I don't, so I don't know if
that is like, you know, how much of that is going on,
but it seems like they certainly don't need to say the whole
thing, right? Do we say that they really should say some of
it? I don't know, you know, but anyway we are more lenient
though. So
but I would conceptually agree with you that, yeah.
So anyway, נכתב ביום ונחתם ביום, בלילה ונחתם בלילה, בלילה ונחתם ביום,
כשר.
nichtav bayom v'nechtam bayom,
balaila v'nechtam balaila, balaila v'nechtam bayom, kasher. So I'm going to diagram
this because we're going
to
go...
So here I'm going to put in נחתם. Nechtam.
You see, I wish we can, you know, live stream this. יום,
Yom,
לילה. Laila.
And this would be נכתב. Nichtav.
Here would be יום. Yom.
This
would be לילה. Laila.
Okay, so this is
our, this is our
grid. So נכתב ביום ונחתם ביום. Nichtav bayom venichtam bayom. So both
of these occurred in the day, right? יום יום, Yom yom, right?
So that would
be כשר. Kasher. That's
good, right? That's best, right? You do everything in, and you know,
during that one day. בלילה ונחתם בלילה. Balaila venichtam balaila. That's also,
I'm just going at the end, כשר, Kasher, right? So לילה, Laila,
both are done at night, also כשר. Kasher. Okay, בלילה ונחתם ביום,
Balaila venichtam bayom, which is the last of those three כשר. Kasher.
So again, בלילה ונחתם ביום, Balaila venichtam bayom, this would also be
good. Because it's Hebrew? I'm sorry? Exactly. Exactly right. So נכתב בלילה
ונחתם ביום, Nichtav balaila venichtam bayom, that would also be
good, right? So what would be the debate? The last case. ביום
ונחתם בלילה. Bayom venichtam balaila.
Right? So נכתב ביום ונחתם בלילה. Nichtav bayom venichtam balaila. So that
is no good, פסול. Pasul. That's the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, right?
So תנא
קמא.
Tanna
Kamma.
However, רבי שמעון מכשיר. Rabbi Shimon Machshir. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says this is
good. Okay. Check out רבי שמעון אומר כל הגיטין שנכתבו ביום ונחתמו
בלילה פסולין. Rabbi Shimon omer kol hagittin shenichtevu bayom venichtamu balaila pesulin.
But רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said normally this case would be פסול.
Pasul. Not this case, normally a גט Get that would have this
would be
פסול, Pasul, חוץ מגיטי נשים, Chutz migittei nashim, with the exception being
גיטי נשים. Gittei nashim. So now we have to understand why, right?
So
we're going to get to, we're going to say it right now.
But what would you think? Let's say it was, remember there's different
types of גיטין, Gittin, different types of שטרות. Shtarot. A גט Get
is like, you know, שטר, Shtar, but there's lots of different types
of שטר. Shtar. Let's say you have a שטר חוב, Shtar chov,
right? Then the שטר חוב, Shtar chov, so as we may remember,
if you have a written document, if you have an oral, you
still have to pay it back regardless of whether there's a document
or not. But if you have an oral document, then the power
of the creditor, meaning the guy who loaned you the money, is
a little bit less than if you have the שטר. Shtar. Because
if you have an oral agreement, then you can only at most
be גובה Goveh from נכסים בני חורין, Nechasim benei chorin, right? Like,
you know, his money. But if you have a שטר, Shtar, you
can also be גובה Goveh from נכסים משועבדים, Nechasim meshubadim, which is
קרקע, Karka, which is land, right? That helps you. So now what
would be the problem? Like if you have basically the idea is
like if it's different days, right? Like let's say, you know, if
it's really not signed, if it's not finished until the following night,
it's technically another day, right? So if you have a regular, if
you have a regular שטר, Shtar, what would be the problem having
it having it like let's say this on Monday and this on
Tuesday?
What would be the problem? Who cares?
The reason would be like if you have a lien on the
guy's property, right? Let's say and it doesn't really take effect until
Tuesday, right? So, you know, and but you're thinking, oh well because
it says Monday, so let's say there was property that was sold
in between then, right? You, you know, you're, it really doesn't take
effect until Tuesday, you don't have any claim on the Monday property,
right? Because it really was Tuesday, but the שטר Shtar says Monday,
so I'm going to get the Monday property, right? Let's say he
sold something during that time. So that would be the problem of
having different, you know, times. Like think about, I mean it's more
stark if I say, you know, 2015 versus 2016, right? But if
if it really was written up in 2015, doesn't really take effect
until 2016, then you're going to say oh wait a minute I
can גובה Goveh it from stuff sold in 2015. No, right? It
didn't really take effect until 2016. You can't you can't, you know,
you can't take this this earlier. I sold that normally. In other
words if, you know, if I sell, if the three of us,
right? I loan I loan, you know, money or you loan, whichever
way it is, take take whichever way you want, and then Jonathan
buys it from one of us, so then the בעל חוב Ba'al
chov comes and says sorry Jonathan, you know, but I'm trying to
collect this debt. But the guy has no money. I know, you
know, I can get land, he has no land either. I know
he sold it to you. He sold it after this loan
occurred. I'm getting it from you. But really he didn't, right? Because,
you know, because you're looking at the document, the document says 2015,
it didn't really happen until 2016. So you bought it fine. So
you have no claim against what was sold to Jonathan. That loan
didn't even happen yet, right? So you don't have a claim on
that. But if really it was, you know, but if it really
happened earlier, then you do. So that's the problem. Are we clear
on this? Yeah, but that's the problem of having two different times.
So, you know, I mean yes, it's just a difference of a
day, but you know, a lot can happen in a day.
So okay fine. So that's why you would have it on a
regular שטר חוב. shtar chov. Now what about a גיטין, gittin, right?
Only for leniency to the woman, I think, because
now when does the leniency take into effect?
We had cases in the past where we made a differentiation between
a regular שטר shtar and a גט get in terms of to
be lenient to the woman. Yeah, so I'm guessing that's it.
Well let's see. I mean the גמרא Gemara will explain the reasons
why. Now remember גט get isn't a שטר חוב, shtar chov, a
גט get is, you know, you're divorced, right? So it's a bit
different. So why are we so worried about this for a גט?
get? So now we'll let's see. איתמר במאי תקנו זמן בגיטין. itmar
bamei tiknu zman begittin. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אמר amar משום mishum
בת אחותו, bat achoto, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish אמר amar משום mishum
פירות. perot. So this is a very important מחלוקת. machloket. Let me
just write it down on here. I would write it down there
but no one can see it. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan משום
mishum בת אחותו, bat achoto, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish משום mishum פירות.
perot. Okay and I'll explain it. So normally you would come to
the logical conclusion if the man and the woman are getting divorced,
there's not particularly that much love there, you know, and he may
not particularly care what happens to her. But let's say he's actually
related to her, because you can actually marry your niece, right, from
תורה. Torah. So let's say he married his niece. So you know,
so forget whether he did marry her, let's just say his niece.
You know, you have good family relations, so you kind of want
to protect your family, right, just in general. You know, especially if
it's a close enough relative. So you know you may feel a
little, what do you call it, paternalistic, you know, or just you
know you just want to take care of her. So now let's
say he actually married her, right? Then you know it didn't work
out, so you're getting divorced.
But let's say she committed adultery, right?
So you might want to protect
her. So how
would she be protected? So like let's
say,
you
know,
let's
take the example, I
like it better than if
it's the
same idea, you
know,
like let's say 2015, I'm making
this like a really crazy example but it just
it's hard for me to write this way, you know, so right?
So really this would be the נכתב nechtav so to speak, and
this would be the נחתם, nechtam, you know, that's our analog. But
basically let's say there was no
זמן, zman, right? Forget the נכתב nechtav and נחתם nechtam for a
second. There's no זמן, zman, right? So no זמן, zman, so she
committed adultery here in 2016, right? There's no
זמן. zman. So she'll say no, no, no, no, I was divorced
back in 2015, here's my גט. get. There's no time in it,
you can say you were divorced whenever it was, right? So
she can never be punished, right?
I was single back then. What do you mean? Really she wasn't
because it was given in 2017. You know what I mean? Like
you get the idea. So that's called שמא יחפה על בת אחותו,
shema yechapeh al bat achoto, you know, try to cover it up
or try to protect her.
That's a
relative
thing. So that's רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan שמא יחפה על בת אחותו,
shema yechapeh al bat achoto, and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish holds פירות.
perot. So
we
know that one of the תקנות takkanot is that the husband can,
there's like the principal and there's like the interest so to speak,
so there's like the פירות perot would be sort of like literally
the food. Let's say you have a tree and there's פירות. perot.
So the husband can get the fruit, the פירות, perot, from this
tree and also... so to
speak, you know, but he can use the fruit. So let’s say
there’s the same idea. So let’s say there’s no זמן zman in
the גט, get, right? Let's
say they really got divorced in 2015,
now it's 2017,
and the husband sold something in 2016, the fruit. He keeps on
selling this fruit. Then she says, wait, give it back to me,
we're divorced in 2015. Then he says, well there's no זמן zman
there, I just divorced you now, right, so I was allowed to
sell everything up
until 2016, only got divorced in 2017, same idea. I mean in
terms of the problem of זמן zman for different reason. He’s not
worried about the בת אחותו bas achoso case, he says the reason's
because of פירות, peiros, right? So this is to protect the woman
because the husband wouldn't, if they really got divorced back here, the
husband wasn't allowed to sell stuff here in 2016. So that’s the
פירות peiros case. Okay, so there’s two different reasons. Obviously they both
agree that you have to write the זמן. zman.
So now let’s see how this plays out. So ריש לקיש מאי
טעמא לא אמר כרבי יוחנן? Reish Lakish mai taama lo amar k'Rabbi
Yochanan? So why is ריש לקיש Reish Lakish who holds פירות peiros
not holding Rabbi
Yochanan that holds you know the I'm going to call it niece
case, בת אחותו? bas achoso? Why not? So the case again which
she commits adultery he wants to protect her because he says אמר
לך, amar lach,
turn the page to the עמוד ב, amud beis, זנות לא שכיחא.
znus lo shechicha. You know,
look I want to have a more
broadly applicable case. So first of all, you know, how many times
will be בת אחותו? bas achoso? And even if that's common, then
to worry because of בת אחותו bas achoso and that she’d be
זונה, zona, commit adultery, and that you know we’re just going to
cover up for her, I’m going to institute a זמן zman at
every single גט get because of the few cases of adultery that
you know you might have to be worried about? So I’m not
that’s not the reason. Fine. So that makes sense. ורבי יוחנן מאי
טעמא לא אמר כריש לקיש? v'Rabbi Yochanan mai taama lo amar k'Reish
Lakish? And you know we ask why doesn't one hold by the
other. So now why does the other not hold by the one?
So in other words why does Rabbi Yochanan who does hold from
this whole בת אחותו bas achoso case not hold like ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish who’s worried about the פירות peiros case, right? קסבר יש
לבעל פירות עד שעת נתינה. kasavar yesh l'baal peiros ad shas nesina.
So
remember there’s three times here.
There’s נכתב nichtav when it was written,
there’s נחתם nichtam when it was signed, and then there’s נתינה nesina
when it was given, right?
You know which I mean more you know now more or less
like these days I think it’s kind of all around the same
time. They go to בית דין, beis din, they write it up,
you know, they sign it and then you know and it’s given
all at that time. But this you know there could definitely be
a big lag and especially let's say you're going overseas, right? You
know that may take quite a while, it take six months, right?
Anyway, so the point was that
if
really right in other words we said that the problem with פירות
peiros was this case, right? They
really get divorced here. Let’s say this is the so this would
be even better. Let’s say this is נכתב, nichtav, this would be
נחתם, nichtam, and this would be ניתן, nitan, right? So let’s say
it was נכתב nichtav in 2015 and נחתם nichtam in 2016 and
given in 2017, right? So we were saying that the whole problem
was what happens in
2016 the middle time. If you really if so the husband is
busy selling up until here if there’s no זמן zman in a
גט, get, let’s say there’s no זמן zman in a גט, get,
they got divorced here, he sold this, he said it's fine, right?
She says no we got divorced here you shouldn't have sold this.
But if we hold
that it doesn’t hold until it doesn’t come into effect until it’s
given, then he was allowed to sell everything over here. You have
until the last possible moment to sell, right? You have like if
a kid is born in 2000 you have that child tax deduction.
The kid is born in this year makes no difference if the
kid was born January 1st or December 31st you can still claim
a $2000 tax deduction per child, right? Doesn't make a difference anywhere
in the year. So same idea I mean so to speak the
same idea for
a גט. get. It’s good up until the last possible moment. So
the husband is allowed to keep on selling and wheeling and dealing
with the פירות peiros until שעת נתינה. shas nesina. So he’s going
to say so yeah he was allowed to sell it here and
and here. We know when it was given so he’s allowed to
sell until the possible moment. So I don't need a זמן zman
because of that. What I do need a זמן zman is because
of the adultery case.
That makes sense?
I mean because also couldn't he always retract until the time he
gives it? He could decide not to
give it yet, that's true.
So then he would retain the property right?
He'd retain use of the property if he can retract. Yeah so
that makes sense until that’s based on what you said that’s a
good point. Okay. So
that's what he holds. So that, so again, so ריש, Reish, so
basically what רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would say
to
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, and so what would he say to the
other, right? So he would say רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan לא שכיח,
lo shchiach, and then he would hold יש לו פירות אזמן נתינה.
yesh lo peirot azman
netina.
So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish does not hold like רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan because he holds that רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan case isn't common,
and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan does not hold like ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish because he's saying ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish case is not a
problem because he can keep on
wheeling
and dealing until the last possible moment so
he
don't get זמן zman because of that.
But he does because of, you know, protectionism. So,
okay, so now we're going to analyze each one. בשלמא לריש לקיש
משום הכי קמכשיר רבי שמעון. Bishlama leReish Lakish mishum hachi kamachshir Rabbi
Shimon. So I understand that according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
would
say it's okay.
Why
would he, why would he say it's okay? Remember there's a מחלוקת,
machlokes, obviously they disagree about something.
So
what I'm going to do is I'm going
to
erase what I wrote yesterday and it's too bad that this isn't
being recorded.
Now again, it's not like we proved that
these are just positions, you know, we didn't cite a ברייתא braisa
that
says שנת נתינה shnat netina or anything like that but we're just
saying this is what he must hold.
You know,
you have these awkward pauses on the
recording
but just erasing stuff over here so I can write it down
which
unfortunately those who are listening to recording will not get the benefit
of having.
All right. So this
is
going to be רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and this is going to be ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. And then
each of them are going to have to explain what the difference
is between רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma,
right? Because we're going to go through both positions and try to
explain what the basis of their מחלוקת machlokes is. Remember רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon was קמכשיר, kamachshir, תנא
קמא
Tanna Kamma
was פוסל, posel, right? In this case. Effectively like, you know, different
days, right? Days, years, whatever. It's like again, I like saying years
because it's, you know, easier to understand. So what we're going to
say is, I'm going to write it down, then I'll explain it.
אין
לו זמן כתיבה.
Ein lo
zman ketiva.
Just I think it'll be easier over here. יש לו פירות אזמן
נתינה. Yesh lo peirot azman netina. Then אין לו זמן כתיבה ein
lo zman ketiva
and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma יש לו אזמן. yesh lo azman.
I think this the way it works.
Okay. So I wrote it down and then I'll explain it.
So again, so now that we understand like, you know, what the
party lines are, if it's a general, you know, יחפה על אחותו
yachpeh al achoto or פירות, peirot, now let's try to understand the
differences between the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
according to each of you, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and רבי יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan. בשלמא לריש לקיש משום הכי קמכשיר רבי שמעון. Bishlama leReish
Lakish mishum hachi kamachshir Rabbi Shimon. So the גמרא Gemara doesn't explain
what that is. I can understand according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
why רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would be okay. Again,
another when you have different dates, right? In other words, the date
that was written versus the date it was signed. So that would
be called מוקדם, mukdam, just to
understand our terminology. מוקדם Mukdam would be sort of like predated, right?
That's what this would be called.
And מאוחר me'uchar would be postdated but anyway so this is effectively
predated. So רש"י Rashi is going to explain why. why
that would be based on the גמרא, Gemara, but anyway, but in
order to understand it, I'll tell you now, because according to רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, why would be predated, if you're holding again, we're
talking about ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish would be
the one that holds פירות, peirot, right? So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says a predated גט get would be okay. What could possibly be
the reason?
The reason is because he holds that from the moment I start
writing it already, right? Remember the three times? There's כתיבה, ketivah, there's
נכתב, nichtav, נחתם, nechtam, and ניתן, nitan, right? נכתב nichtav is the
very beginning, נחתם nechtam would be, you know, somewhere in the middle,
and then ניתן nitan would be at the very end. So רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says I don't care it's predated, right? Like, in
other words, which means, like, you know, 2016 it was written, it
means 2015 it was written, right? In my case before, 2015, 2016,
2017, it was written 2015, that's okay. Why? Because he holds the
בעל, ba'al, you know, once he starts writing it, the בעל ba'al
has no rights anymore.
Well, I think it's until he gives it. No, once once...
that's where they agree. That's...
רבי שמעון... Rabbi Shimon... no, they disagree. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma disagree on a predated גט. get.
We're talking about ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. Yeah, I'm saying ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish agrees with רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. He says...
Not that... this is not ריש לקיש Resh Lakish agrees with רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish is explaining... you know, it's
a מחלוקת, machlokes, they don't agree. It's not a matter of ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish agreeing with רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan agreeing with the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. They're both trying
to explain what, you know, what the reason is. Why do you
have a זמן zman in the גט, get, right? Why have it
at all, right? So he said, oh, because of these פירות, peirot,
you know, versus שמא יחפה על בת אחותו. shema yechapeh al bas
achoso. Now so okay, but a predated גט get is a מחלוקת
machlokes between תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, right?
So why would רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say it's okay, תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma says it's not? רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's okay
because he holds, you know, let's say the case of the... let's
say the case of, remember we had our case that I'm going
to come to be גובה goveh from Jonathan, right? Because, you know,
because the property was sold back early and you're saying, no, it
really took into effect, it really took into effect later. If it
took into effect later, then I can't go to Jonathan, right? רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, no, it doesn't take into effect later. It
takes effect earlier. From the moment I start writing it, the בעל
ba'al loses all rights, right? So let's say the wife then wants
to go say, hey, you sold this this, you know, you... I
know that I just got the גט get now, 2017, but you
sold this stuff in 2016 and I was divorced in 2015, right?
She may not, you know, so... so then רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says you're right. Really, she was divorced 2015. I don't care that
it was given later, the divorce... I mean, it's really we're talking
about when she can come and get the property. I'm not going
to... they're not even going to get into when she's actually divorced.
That may be different than when, you know, the בעל ba'al loses
rights to the פירות. peirot. But whatever. But the point being though,
the husband loses all rights to the פירות peirot from the time
it was written. So she wants to go, it was given 2017,
she wants to go back to 2016, that was a case where,
you know, Jonathan bought the property, she can. That's what רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon holds. That's why he doesn't worry about it. If her
whole reason is to protect, you know, protect purchasers and whatever it
is, right?
They're not protected, right? Meaning, like, it doesn't
apply. According to
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, 2004, okay, I mean, you obviously you have
to have a זמן, zman, otherwise you can go back to the
beginning of time and say, you know, we're divorced in
1992, right? But you know, so you have to have some sort
of זמן. zman. But the point is once it starts being written
and באחד
בשבת,
be'echad
beshabbos, be whatever it is, right? Then the בעל ba'al already loses
rights to the
פירות. peirot.
There's a note here that says it says it's when it's given
that...
Not according to רבי
שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon.
We'll explain it, you'll see. I mean, but you're going with me?
Forget the note. Does that make sense? Pardon me? Does what I'm
saying making sense?
It does, I'm just... okay, okay, I'm with you. Keep going.
So that so... so רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying that from
the from the moment that it's written, the בעל ba'al loses rights
to the פירות. peirot. So therefore, he's okay from predated. Yeah, because
you know what? From the moment it's written, the בעל ba'al loses
פירות. peirot. So I don't care that it's that it that the
גט get is dated from that time. If the whole reason is
פירות, peirot, which what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says,
then we're good.
I think what they're discussing is is what would be the reason
why why we have the dated גט get at all? Yeah. And
the reason is because the בעל ba'al in giving the גט get
in in creating a distinct time frame between the writing and the
and the signing and the giving may be able to play have
some shenanigans to his advantage. Right.
But according to ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, right.
But according
to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, if he plays around with the date,
he's disadvantaging his intent, which is to protect his
niece.
Yeah, well, we didn't get to that yet, but yeah, but that's
next.
But according to ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, which is about the
פירות, peirot, right, if that's... But
according to רב יוחנן, Rav Yochanan, it's until the giving, right?
But we didn't get to that yet. We didn't get to that.
But I mean the גמרא Gemara will explain itself. So let me,
if you want, I'll explain it all now.
No, no, no, no.
I'm sorry. Okay, but I understand according to ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would be מכשיר machshir because again, right, because
the בעל baal loses all rights from time it's written. So therefore,
you know, that's it, right? I don't mind that it's predated because
once the moment it's that's it, that's when it stops for the
בעל. baal. So אלא ella רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan מאי טעמא mai
ta'ama דרבי שמעון d'Rabbi Shimon דמכשיר? d'machshir? So according to רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, according to רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
I mean, holds, you know, why would רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say
it's okay? If your again רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan the whole point
was that they want to protect, right, and this is what Jonathan
said, that's why I said just wait a second. So why, you
know, if you want to protect, but wait, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says it's okay if it's predated,
that you shoot yourself in the foot, right? If you want to
protect somebody you want it to take effect later, you know, you
know what I mean?
Like why would you... so
why would that be? So אמר לך amar lach רב יוחנן, Rav
Yochanan, לרבי שמעון l'Rabbi Shimon לא קאמינא. lo kamina. Right, my I
don't work I'm not dealing with רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. I can't
answer that. כי קאמינא ki kamina אליבא דרבנן. aliba d'rabbanan. I'm
no I'm going according to רבנן. Rabbanan. So
what do we mean by that? So basically,
let me just read this. שכתב רבנן כסברי זמן משום בת אחותו.
shekatav Rabbanan kasavri zman mishum bat achoto. Right. So the רבנן Rabbanan
say, you know, he's explaining the רבנן's Rabbanan reasons for saying it's
a problem. So
yeah,
so for that reason, right, because then you would start to be
protect, you know, you want to protect her, so but she's really
not, you know, divorced, you know, or depending on which way you
go. But anyway, but the point being yeah, you want to protect
her, so therefore you're going to play these games. No, so you
know, so that's why we say it's... that's why we say you
have to have a זמן, zman, right, because you're going to claim
that you were divorced earlier when it really was later. Right? So
you know,
so but now what about, you know, what do you do about
פירות peirot though? Right? Because I mean because okay fine, I understand
that's why it is, but you know, but what about our issue
of פירות? peirot? Let's get back to the פירות peirot for a
second, right? What would they say about that? Right? You understand where
I'm getting at because I mean the בעל baal does have rights
to the פירות peirot for a certain amount of time, right? And
the...
so you know,
so basically,
you know, we understand the whole thing about בת אחותו, bat achoto,
we understand that but what would you do about the פירות? peirot?
Now what we mentioned is a second before that יש פירות עד
זמן
נתינה,
yeish peirot ad zman
netina, right?
So רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon still going to say... he's not going
to go according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
can still be that he holds אין לו, ein lo, you know,
that the husband loses rights from the זמן כתיבה. zman ketiva. That's
why he's okay with this, right?
ורבנן v'Rabbanan as we said before, you know, already, would say, you
know, יש פירות עד זמן נתינה. yeish peirot ad zman netina. So
that can't be the reason, right? So therefore, you know, it's a...
it's a בת אחותו bat achoto case.
I don't know if that confused you or not. Anyway, but the
point is, as I said before, they, the רבנן Rabbanan hold that
you have it, you know,
until it's given, right? So if you have it until it's given
then, you know, that's why this... that's why they don't hold from
the whole פירות peirot case. Remember, that's what he said, this is
according to רב יוחנן. Rav Yochanan. רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan doesn't hold
from the whole פירות peirot case because he holds that you can
have it until זמן נתינה, zman netina, right? So if you have
it until זמן נתינה, zman netina, then you shouldn't potentially have a
problem
with the זמן. zman. Oh, that's why he holds בת אחותו, bat
achoto, right? That'd be the problem. And therefore we don't like that,
so you know, it has to be, you know, because you would
come to protect it, so therefore, you know, that's my reason to
have זמן. zman. So that's why they don't want, you know, and
so, you know, we don't like these whole predated
things because you're going to come to protect... even though it's... again,
take the year example, you know,
like that if you have predated, it doesn't really take effect later,
you know, you're going to come to protect her. So that's why
they hold בת אחותו, bat achoto, but regarding פירות, peirot,
they hold יש פירות עד זמן נתינה, yeish peirot ad zman netina,
which is so that can't be the reason why we have
a תקנה takanah in the גט get for זמן. zman. So but
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon does, right, he's not going according to רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, right, remember he's... that doesn't work, right? So but
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon though would hold that... that you know, that
he
loses... And a predated גט. get. Yeah.
Right? So they're talking about our משנה Mishnah deals with a predated
גט, get, but our גמרא Gemara begins discussing why do you need
the date.
Right. And then then he transferred it based on that, read our
משנה. Mishnah.
Yeah, they backtrack to the משנה Mishnah to validate each position or
not.
Right. Right. So that's so רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Okay, so I
think we're good there.
So אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, read that again: אליבא דרבי
שמעון לא קמינא קמינא דרבנן. Aliba d'Rabbi Shimon lo kamina kamina d'Rabbanan.
Fine. All right. So now we analyze רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So
בשלמא Bishlama לרבי יוחנן, l'Rabbi Yochanan, היינו דאיכא hainu d'ika בין רבי
שמעון לרבנן. bein Rabbi Shimon l'Rabbanan. So now I understand what the
what the difference is. That
like like I said, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon I can, you know,
can potentially be holding this פירות peirot issue, right? And תנא קמא
Tanna Kama is holding this בת אחותו bathato issue. That's what they're
disagreeing about.
אלא לריש לקיש, Ella l'Resh Lakish, מה איכא ma ika בין רבי
שמעון לרבנן? bein Rabbi Shimon l'Rabbanan? So but according to ריש לקיש,
Resh Lakish, what what are they disagreeing about?
So because again ריש לקיש Resh Lakish is saying it's nothing to
do with בת אחותו. bathato. So all has to be about פירות.
peirot. So what is the basis of their disagreement? So it obviously
has to be in terms of timing, right? So how does that
work out? פירי דבשעת כתיבה ועד שעת חתימה איכא בינייהו. Peirei d'vishaat
ketiva ve'ad sha'at chatima ika beinei'u.
So remember there are as I said, there are there are three
times, right?
There
was כתיבה, ketiva, חתימה chatima and נתינה, netina, right? But our משנה
Mishnah is dealing with נכתב nichtav and נחתם, nechtam, right? So it
has to be something about that. Not שעת נתינה. sha'at netina. So
what would be the difference? So the difference is רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon would hold as before with רבי Rabbi as we said by
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that the בעל baal loses from זמן כתיבה.
zman ketiva. So
therefore you're going to say, oh, what about 2016 property? Right, remember
that? 2015, 16 and 17. You know, 2015 was נכתב, nichtav, 2016
was, yeah, נחתם nechtam and then 2017 was delivered. Forget about 2017,
right? Because we're not dealing with שעת נתינה sha'at netina for a
moment. But we're dealing for two different times. So רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon holds that אין לו מזמן כתיבה. ein lo mizman ketiva. From
the time it's written, the husband loses all rights to the פירות.
peirot. So then she's going to give this predated גט get and
say, "Ah, ah, you couldn't have sold," and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
saying, "That's right, you couldn't have sold," right? But תנא קמא Tanna
Kama so therefore he's okay with it. Right? Predated גט. get. But
תנא קמא Tanna Kama would hold no, like he he has until
it's signed. So it was signed in 2016, then she's going to
bring this predated גט, get, "Ah, you couldn't sell," and the חכמים
Chachamim say, "Hmm. No, signed." Right? Forget about forget about delivered. Let's
say in this case the signing and delivered happened on the same
day. But the but the writing happened a year before, right? So
so and the signing and the
witnesses, in other words the writing is he didn't sign it yet.
It's just.
He wrote it, you know, 2015 and again I'm I'm doing using
a stark example, but our example was just between the day and
the night. The following night. Or even the next day. But 2000
2015 it was signed, 2016 I mean 2016 it was written, 2016
it was signed and let's say it was delivered and also in
2016, right? So then but you know
but at the same the beginning of 2015 let's say it was
you know it was it was written and then the end of
2015 you know it was signed and delivered. What about all the
rest of it? In June, right? The middle, right? So she's going
to come with this she's going to come with this predated גט,
get, right? I'm going to call we're calling it predated, right? That
says, "Oh, from the beginning of 2015 already, you know you you
you couldn't have sold anything." So I'm going to go after the
June property, right?
And so רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, "That's right, you can go
after the June property." Because from the moment he starts writing, January
1st 2015, the husband loses all rights. So Jonathan, you're out, right?
You bought in mid-2015, tough luck, right? But תנא קמא Tanna Kama
holds no, the husband can sell can use everything until the end
of 2015 when it was signed. So now Jonathan would be out
when he shouldn't have been, right? So she's going to come and
say, "Jonathan, you know, hey, it says the beginning of 2015, that's
what that's when it's that's when it was, you know, written." And
then but you know so then Jonathan would be out and the
תנא קמא Tanna Kama holds, you know, that that's actually a problem
because Jonathan is entitled to it because really the husband you know
you know the husband's allowed to wheel and deal until שעת חתימה.
sha'at chatima. So you're going to go come and you know and
the purchaser you know is going to be out. That's why that's
why the תנא קמא Tanna Kama holds that this predated גט get
is פסול pasul for that for that exact reason. Makes sense? We
good?
Yes?
I got confused between the giving and the signing.
Well I just again I just did it to like make it
very stark, maybe that that's what maybe that's what confused you, but
the I got confused
because in the משנה Mishnah it says the signing, right?
Yeah, but you know but again like but we we threw that
in
there. So that's right, but the
משנה *Mishna* didn't.
The distinction was not being made in the משנה *Mishna*, the distinction
was being made in the
גמרא *Gemara*. Okay. But the idea is, the idea is to explain
until when he has rights to the פירות *Perot* and then read
that back into a מחלוקת *Machloket* about giving. So like we just
said, in other words, at least it makes the most sense according
to ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*. He's saying the whole thing has to
do with פירות *Perot*, right? And so therefore what's the difference between
רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* and תנא קמא *Tana Kamma*? רבי שמעון *Rabbi
Shimon* holds that from the moment it started to be written, the
husband doesn't have any rights. So therefore if she brings a predated
גט *Get*, that's totally fine, because the husband already lost the rights
from the very beginning. תנא קמא *Tana Kamma* holds husband has rights
longer. She brings a predated גט *Get*, then it's a problem, because
husband really actually did have rights to sell it during that time.
So that's the basis of their מחלוקת *Machloket* as to when the
husband has rights. So according to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* though, no,
that's where this נתינה *Netina* came in. You know, the תנא קמא
*Tana Kamma* will hold you actually had פירות *Perot* עד זמן נתינה
*ad Zman Netina*. So you can go be wheeling and dealing in
2017, right? So therefore,
it can't be the reason why a predated גט *Get* is פסול
*Pasul*.
He does hold that a predated גט *Get* is פסול *Pasul*. It's
not a פירות *Perot* issue, rather it's a בת אחותו *Bat Achoto*
issue. That's what we're worried about. And רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says
no, you know, I'm okay with it because it's a totally פירות
*Perot* issue. If it's a totally
פירות *Perot* issue, why is he okay with it? Because he holds
that the husband loses rights very early on, זמן כתיבה *Zman Ketiva*.
So the only question I have is רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* saying
it only goes into effect when it's signed
or
when it's delivered?
I would think that it's still when it's, I think everyone holds
that the actual divorce, and this is where I'm trying to make
this distinction but I have to research it, the actual divorce I
think goes into effect when it's delivered according to everybody. The question
is, when do פירות *Perot* kick in? Do they kick in when
it's delivered? Do they kick in when it's signed? Do they kick
in when it's written?
Right, but it only goes,
it only has
reality after it's given, right?
Yes, that's what I think. I mean,
I didn't see the answer to it, but that's, you know, oh
man, it's late. So alright, I'm going to finish.
We'll finish up in a moment.
This will be quick, this last part. Okay, so that's the difference.
זמן נתינה *Zman Netina*, right?
I've got an appointment at eight.
Okay, that's fine. No, I'm going to, this is going to be
like two minutes. ואיכא דאמרי השתא מיהא להו דאתמר מאימתי מוציאין פירות
*Ve'ika d'amri hashta miha lehu d'itmar me'eimatai motzi'in perot* רבי יוחנן אמר
*Rabbi Yochanan amar* משעת כתיבה *mishat ketiva*, right? And ריש לקיש אמר
*Reish Lakish amar* משעת נתינה *mishat netina*, right? ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*
now, this is a ברייתא *Baraita* that says נתינה *Netina*, this says,
let's concentrate on the תנא קמא *Tana Kamma* for a second, כתיבה
*Ketiva*, which is not this, and this is not this, right? So
איפוך *Efoch*, switch them around. Alright. So this would be נתינה *Netina*,
this would be כתיבה *Ketiva*, right? So that's okay.
Alright, I'll stop over
here, since it's already late. Sorry we got a late start with
this livestreaming thing. But at least it's recorded.
Technology when it works is great, when it doesn't...
Yeah, let's just make sure we got the reason why רבי שמעון
*Rabbi Shimon* differs from the תנא קמא *Tana Kamma*
and מכשיר *Machshir* it.
Right?
I'm sorry? I mean, the גמרא *Gemara* just walks back the issues
to what is the basis of the מחלוקת *Machloket*? Why would רבי
שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* have different from the תנא קמא *Tana Kamma*?
Right. Bye guys.
Okay,
have a good one.
I really don't know how to get out of this here.
In virtual space.
Just turn the lights and look for the door.
We'll stay on, I'll go stay on. No, let's go.
We will, we'll lock it up. Goodnight. Have a good day.
Goodnight Hal.
Goodnight. Goodnight to Texaco. You remember Hal? No, who's Hal?
Remember Hal the computer in? Yeah.
Oh right. And remember David
and Chet? Goodnight to Texaco. Yeah. Goodnight David, goodnight Chet, goodnight to
Texaco.
Alright, I really gotta run.
Did you get it off?
I don't even know, but I have to make my train.
So, you have to what?
I have to make my train.
Okay. There is a chart here.
I'll just, you can do me a favor,
if you get a second here, can you just like make sure
that this thing is like off?
Well, I can try to get.
No, I mean, you know, I don't want because
usually he leaves the, he leaves the... Rabbi רבי *Rabbi* Winzer leaves
the desktop up. Close this stuff. See if I can get this
moving. Okay, I think I have it. There it is. Thank you
very much for joining us.
It was a pleasure having you. We learned so much about the
פרשה *parsha* and especially about the ימים נוראים *Yamim Noraim*. It is
a זכות *zechus* for us. Wishing you a גמר חתימה טובה *gmar
chatima tova* and a safe trip. Okay, I am going to hit
stop.